18 Prince Street | Cambridge, MA | 02139 laura.m.bacon@gmail.com | +1 781 660 6660

QUALIFICATIONS SUMMARY

Strong advising and interpersonal skills, backed by broad range of professional experience (Peace Corps, White House Fellowship, social impact investing, university research programs) and personal experience (mentor, counselor, cellist, triathlete, marathon runner, cancer survivor). Demonstrated ability to live and work diverse environments, including multiple years living abroad and extensive travel. Deep familiarity with Harvard College and the residential House system.

EDUCATION

2007–2009 Harvard Kennedy School Cambridge, MA

Degree: Master of Public Policy: Political & Economic Development

Awards: Catherine B. Reynolds Fellowship for Social Entrepreneurship; Cultural Bridge Fellowship

1998–2002 Harvard College Cambridge, MA

Degree: Bachelor of Arts: Psychology, with honors

Awards: Phi Beta Kappa, John Harvard & Elizabeth Cary Agassiz Scholarships

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2013-present Omidyar Network, Governance & Citizen Engagement Initiative Director

London, UK

- Invest financial, strategic, network, and human capital in transparency & accountability organizations globally
- Commission research on open data impact; lead monitoring and evaluation / social impact tracking
- Serve on board of multiple organizations, including World Wide Web Foundation, Open Contracting Partnership
- Devise and implement global policy and advocacy strategies; manage a multi-million-dollar portfolio

2011–2013 Innovations for Successful Societies Research Center, Princeton University Princeton, NJ Associate Director

- Directed production of 70+ case studies on public sector governance and accountability
- Developed strategic plan and multi-year agenda for center activity
- Supervised production staff, research team, and contractors; managed all workflow and collaborations
- Oversaw website design, social media activity, digital newsletter, other communications and outreach

2009–2010 White House Fellowship, Obama administration

Washington, DC

White House Fellow (Office of the Secretary at U.S. Department of Energy, DOE)

- Selected from 1,000+ applicants as one of 15 Fellows appointed by President Obama
- Prepared policy memoranda, presentations, speeches, and briefing docs for DOE leadership team
- Co-designed and launched Women and Energy Initiative; built strategy for DOE Council for Women and Girls
- Designed, planned, and executed multi-stakeholder Cyber Security Summit
- Served as Secretariat for Operations Management Council (top leadership decision-making forum)
- Helped craft DOE Management Principles and High Priority Performance Goals

2008–2009 Women's Legislative Caucus, Liberia

Monrovia, Liberia

Technical Advisor and Researcher (part-time for graduate school thesis)

- Produced recommendations document for gender parity based on field and desk research
- Conducted interviews with stakeholders, created talking points widely used by Caucus
- Drafted legislation designed to increase women's political representation

18 Prince Street | Cambridge, MA | 02139 laura.m.bacon@gmail.com | +1 781 660 6660

2008 Ministry of Gender and Development, Liberia

Monrovia, Liberia

Cultural Bridge Fellow, Advisor to Minister (full-time in summer during graduate school)

- Conducted management audit; recommendations implemented by ministry
- Created ministry resource packets to be distributed to senior ministry staff and president's cabinet
- Designed and facilitated leadership workshops for senior management; wrote ministerial speeches
- Prepared National Women's Conference Report and Women's Plan of Action

2005–2007 Center for Public Leadership, Harvard Kennedy School

Cambridge, MA

Research Fellow

- Managed major research projects on public policy, leadership, and psychology
- Facilitated co-curricular programs for leadership development initiative
- Co-authored successful research grant proposals
- Coordinated international conference on leadership across boundaries
- Designed studies, conducted qualitative and quantitative data analysis

2005–2009 Harvard Leadership Centers and Journals

Cambridge, MA

Researcher, Editor, and Consultant on leadership (part-time)

- Evaluated leadership development program for Center for Public Leadership
- Wrote evaluation report for Harvard Leadership Task Force
- Edited leadership journal, Compass; conducted research for advertorials in Harvard Business Review

2002–2005 United States Peace Corps

Daggo and Guidan Karo, Niger

Natural Resource Management Volunteer

- Coordinated founding of community grain bank and helped establish farmers' cooperative
- Designed and ran regional conferences, health education camps, and educational field trips
- Led Young Girls' Scholarship Program as regional and national coordinator
- Created six microfinance groups for teenage girls
- Founded rural youth travel soccer league; designed and led HIV/AIDS lessons for the teams
- Trained 150 new Peace Corps Volunteers in cross-cultural and technical skills
- Developed and conducted women's food security project evaluation

2001 Dean's Council, Harvard Summer School

Cambridge, MA

Director of Activities Office (full-time summer position)

- Supervised staff; oversaw the work of 120 student proctors; managed office website
- Coordinated cultural, social and leisure activities for 5,000 students; managed budget
- Implemented 50 trips throughout New England for international student body

2000–2001 Harvard University, Psychology Department

Cambridge, MA

Research Assistant for Professor Richard Hackman (part-time during undergraduate studies)

- Analyzed trends in organizational behavior
- Course assistant for advanced undergraduate class

1999 Let's Go Travel Guides

Cambridge, MA

Associate Editor (full-time summer position)

- Edited two best-selling guides; supervised ten researchers abroad
- Designed field research strategies and crafted itineraries

18 Prince Street | Cambridge, MA | 02139 laura.m.bacon@gmail.com | +1 781 660 6660

VOLUNTEERISM AND MENTORSHIP

2016-2017 **Pastoral Care Team, New Unity Unitarian Church**

London, UK

Counselor

• Trained in active listening, suicide prevention, eating disorders, etc.; confidentially counsel those in need of support

2010–present **Big Brothers Big Sisters**

Volunteer

• Spend quality time (talking, trips, meals, homework, cello duets) as a big sister to a fabulous young woman

2009–2010 Higher Achievement (after-school academic program)

Washington, DC

Advisor and Volunteer

• Provided strategic guidance to program leaders on development and outreach; tutored and mentored young scholars

2005–2009 Leverett House, Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Resident Tutor in Psychology, Music, Photography, Public Service, and LGBTQ Issues

- Lived with 450 undergraduate students; advised students and handled crises; coordinated concerts and exhibits
- Advised, mentored, and closely supervised 40 undergraduate students; wrote letters of recommendation

2005–2009 Radcliffe Mentorship Program, Harvard University

Cambridge, MA

Mentor and Member of Advisory Board

- Counseled and advised undergraduate women; met weekly to discuss career goals, academics, personal life, etc.
- As member of Advisory Board, planned events and facilitated mentor / mentee matching process

1999 – 2002 Phillips Brooks House, Harvard Public Service

Cambridge and Boston, MA

Multi-sector Volunteer

- Led music education of inner-city youth; served as mentor and cello tutor for low-income family
- Overnight volunteer at urban student-run homeless shelter

1998–2002 Harvard-Radcliffe Orchestra

Cambridge, MA

President and Associate Principal Cellist

• Produced six concerts per year; coordinated 100-piece orchestra; managed budget; supervised committee of 20

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Bacon, L.M. (2017). "Why We Invested: Tactical Technology Collective." Medium.com.

Pyare, S. & **Bacon**, **L.M.** (2017). "A New Era for Investigative Journalism. Why We Invested: International Consortium of Investigative Journalists." Medium.com

Bacon, L.M. (2016). "If You Build It... Will They Come?" Medium.com

Bacon, L.M. (2016). "Why We Invested: The B Team." Medium.com

Bacon, L.M. (2015). "Liberia's Gender-Sensitive Police Reform: Improving Representation and Responsiveness in a Post-Conflict Setting." *International Peacekeeping*, 22:4, 372-397.

Bacon, L.M. (2013). "Open Contracting is a Game-Changer: Opening Up Governments & Busting Silos." Open Government Partnership.

Bacon, L.M. & Majeed, R. (2012). "The Anti-Godfather." Foreign Policy.com.

Woldemariam, M., Widner, J., & **Bacon**, **L.M.** (2012). "Restructuring Service Delivery: Johannesburg, South Africa, 1996–2001." Innovations for Successful Societies, Princeton University.

18 Prince Street | Cambridge, MA | 02139 laura.m.bacon@gmail.com | +1 781 660 6660

Bacon, L.M. (2012). "Building an inclusive, responsive national police service: Gender-sensitive reform in Liberia, 2005–2011." Innovations for Successful Societies, Princeton University.

Bacon, L.M. & Majeed, R. (2012). "Palermo Renaissance, Part 1: Rebuilding Civic Identity and Reclaiming a City from the Mafia, 1993–2000." Innovations for Successful Societies, Princeton University.

Majeed, R. & **Bacon**, **L.M.** (2012). "Palermo Renaissance, Part 2: Reforming City Hall, 1993–2000." Innovations for Successful Societies, Princeton University.

Majeed, R. & **Bacon**, **L.M.** (2012). "Palermo Renaissance, Part 3: Strengthening Municipal Companies, 1993–2000." Innovations for Successful Societies, Princeton University.

Bacon, L. M., Applegarth, C., Edwards, A., Kennedy, K., Schieffer, S., & Yang, L. (2009). "Is Development in the Details? The Oprah Winfrey Leadership Academy for Girls," adapted for publication as a teaching case, Harvard Kennedy School of Government.

Pittinsky, T. L., **Bacon, L. M.,** & Welle, B. (2007). "The Great Women Theory of Leadership? Perils of positive stereotypes and precarious pedestals." In B. Kellerman and D. Rhode (Eds.), *Women and Leadership: The State of Play and Strategies for Change*. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass.

Pittinsky, T. L., Bacon, L. M., & Gary, L. (2007). "Beyond Tolerance." Tikkun.

Pittinsky, T. L., Rosenthal, S. A., **Bacon, L. M.,** Montoya, R. M., & Zhu, W. (2006). "National Public Leadership Index 2006: A National Study of Confidence in Leadership." Harvard Kennedy School, Cambridge, Massachusetts.

Pittinsky, T. L., **Bacon, L. M.,** & Zhu, W. (2006). "A Model for the Development of Public Leadership." Gallup Leadership Institute Summit. Washington, DC.

SELECTED PRESENTATIONS

Open Data: From Principles to Practice. January 18, 2017. Presentation at conference: "UN World Data Forum." Cape Town, South Africa.

Transparency, Accountability & Participation: Deepening the Evidence Base. January 31, 2014. Presentation at conference: "Data & Accountability for the Post-2015 Development Framework."

Data Revolution: Follow the Money. November 29, 2013. Presentation at conference: "Data for Development". Royal Society, London, UK.

Gender-Sensitive Policing in Liberia. December 12, 2013. Presentation at workshop: "Good Aid in Hard Places: What Has Worked in Fragile Contexts." Helsinki, Finland.

Cities and State Performance. September 21, 2012. Presentation at conference: "Building Government Accountability & Leading Reform." Princeton University.

Tackling Corruption in Palermo: Fighting the Mafia and Reclaiming a City. August 7, 2012. Presentation at conference: "Institutionalizing government: international, comparative perspectives on corruption." Johannesburg, South Africa.

Experiments and Innovations in Institutional Design and Organization of the Public Service. August 4, 2012. Presentation at conference: "Planning ahead: A Gauteng Public Service." Emoyeni, Parktown, South Africa.

Gender-Sensitive Reform in Liberia's National Police. March 14, 2012. Presentation at Indaba, a weekly discussion on Africa-related topics. "Lessons from Liberia: Learning from Case Studies on Liberia's Post-conflict Police Reform

18 Prince Street | Cambridge, MA | 02139 laura.m.bacon@gmail.com | +1 781 660 6660

and Civil Service Reform." Princeton University.

Reflections on the White House Fellowship. March 4, 2012. Sermon, Unitarian Universalist Church. Weymouth, MA.

Gender and Development in Liberia: A View from the Ground. October 9, 2008. Presentation, Women and Public Policy Program, Harvard Kennedy School, Cambridge, MA.

Inspired by Women and Girls of Niger: Memories of a Returned Peace Corps Volunteer. March 8, 2008. Presentation at symposium: "Crisis, Creativity, and Courage: Protecting Women's Rights; Promoting Women's Health." Women's Day Symposium at Harvard Medical School. Boston, MA.

One Dollar a Day: From African Mud Hut to Cambridge Red Brick. February 1, 2007. Presentation at South Shore Cluster Meeting of Unitarian Universalist Churches in Massachusetts.

A Model for the Development of Public Leadership: Avoiding the Synecdochic Fallacy. September 8, 2006. Presentation at Gallup Leadership Institute Summit. Washington, DC.

Engendering Equality: A Discussion on Women in the Developing World. April 29, 2006. Presentation, International Relations Week, sponsored by the Harvard International Relations Council. Cambridge, MA.

The Personal Side to Peace Corps: Living in a Rural Village in Niger. January 22, 2006. Sermon, First Parish Unitarian Universalist Church. Watertown, MA.

Subjectivity of the Other: Reading African News Stories. October 16, 2005. Sermon, Unitarian Universalist Church. Weymouth, MA.

Serving in West Africa; Life and Work in Daggo. Various presentations, 2003, Abigail Adams School; Academy Avenue School, Old South Union Church Youth Group; Briarwood Assisted Living Center.

HONORS AND FELLOWSHIPS

2009–2010	White House Fellowship
2009	Honorable mention for Most Outstanding Thesis, Harvard Kennedy School
2009	Research/travel grant from Women and Public Policy Program (WAPPP), Harvard University
2009	Research/travel grant from Ash Institute for Democratic Governance and Innovation
2008	WAPPP Cultural Bridge Fellowship for work / travel to Liberia
2008	Invited to St. Gallen Symposium in Switzerland for essay selected as one of the best student entries
2007–2009	Catherine B. Reynolds Fellowship for Social Entrepreneurship, Harvard Kennedy School
2006–2007	Research Fellowship, Center for Public Leadership, Harvard Kennedy School
2005	Community Grain Bank project commended with official inauguration day by Republic of Niger
2002	Inducted to Phi Beta Kappa
1998-2002	John Harvard & Elizabeth Cary Agassiz Scholarships

OTHER QUALIFICATIONS, SKILLS, PERSONAL INTERESTS

- Athletic: Completed multiple triathlons, half and full marathons, AIDS Bike Ride through Niger (reaching 8,500 villagers), and 350-mile AIDS Ride from New York to Boston
- Musical: Cellist in multiple musical ensembles: Sinfonia Tamesa in London (2015–2017), Bravura Philharmonic (2010–2013), Boston Philharmonic Orchestra (2006–2009), Harvard University Brahms Society Orchestra (1998–2006), MIT Chamber Music Society (2006–2007), and initiated fundraising concert series for Indian orphanage and Nigerien girls' scholarship
- Languages: English (native); French and Hausa (intermediate); German and Spanish (basic)
- Computer: Proficient in SPSS, STATA, Microsoft Office (Excel, PowerPoint, Word, Outlook)
- Style guide knowledge: Chicago Manual of Style, Associated Press, APA